<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The carpenters rule, or, a booke shewing many plain waies, truly to measure ordinarie timber, and other extraordinarie sollids, or timber with a detection of sundrie great errors, generally committed by carpenters and others in measuring of timber; tending much to the buyers great losse. Published especially for the good of the Companie of Carpenters in London, and others also; ... By Richard More carpenter.</title>
            <author>More, Richard, carpenter.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07688</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18075</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101895</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837698</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837698</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2036</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07688)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2036)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1028:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The carpenters rule, or, a booke shewing many plain waies, truly to measure ordinarie timber, and other extraordinarie sollids, or timber with a detection of sundrie great errors, generally committed by carpenters and others in measuring of timber; tending much to the buyers great losse. Published especially for the good of the Companie of Carpenters in London, and others also; ... By Richard More carpenter.</title>
                  <author>More, Richard, carpenter.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 56 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kingston,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lumber --  Mensuration --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2036:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2036:1"/>
            <p>THE CA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>NTERS RVLE, Or, A BOOKE SHEWING MANY <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> waies, truly to meaſure ordinarie Timber, and other extraordinarie ſollids, or Timber: WITH A DETECTION OF SVNDRIE great errors, generally committed by Carpenters and others in meaſuring of Timber; tending much to the buyers great loſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PVBLISH<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ESPECIALLY FOR THE GOOD of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Carpenters in London, and others alſo; and is very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for</hi> Maſons, Shipwrights, Ioyners, <hi>and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to meaſure Timber and Board, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> other ſuperficies and ſollids.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>HARD MORE Carpenter.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Imprinted by FELIX KYNGSTON. 1602.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2036:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2036:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR HENRY BILLINGSLEY Knight, Alderman of the Citie <hi>of London.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worſhipfull, when I had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten conſidered the great errors, and by error the great loſſe comming to this Citie, in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring of Timber after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wayes; and had long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected ſome mans indeuour for redreſſe, but ſaw none: I was in a ſort prouoked (though the vnfitteſt of a number) to attempt this thing. And becauſe it is not otherwiſe likely, but that I in this caſe, ſhall haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny oppoſers: I haue therefore emboldned my ſelfe, humbly to deſire your worſhips protection: crauing alſo your fauourable acceptance, of this my poore labour; that ſo it may be the better accepted for the common good.</p>
            <p>Neither is my deſire, only to entreate your worſhips fauour and protection, but alſo to teſtifie my dutifull thankfulnes for your great paines and no ſmall coſt, in
<pb facs="tcp:2036:3"/>publiſhing in our Engliſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Euclide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Elements of Geometrie.</hi> A booke, from which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> well may, ſo my ſelfe needes muſt confeſſe, that I haue receiued all that little inſight in Geometry, which I haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained vnto. Yea ſuch is that booke (as I may well ſay) that if mens tongues ſhould be ſilent, yet their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons would not ſpare, plainly to declare the worthines thereof, to the praiſe of your labours. And thus in all duetie, crauing your worſhips protection of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſmall fruite of your owne labours; crauing alſo pardon for my boldneſſe, I humbly take my leaue: deſiring God to bleſſe and keepe you in all good eſtate, to the glorie of his name, the benefit of the Common-wealth, and the good of your ſelfe, in this life and the next.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your VVorſhips <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> all dutie</hi> RICHARD MORE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2036:3"/>
            <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVL, THE MASTER, WARDENS, AND Aſſiſtants of the Companie of Carpenters of the Citie of London: And to all other the curteous Readers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter I had long conſidered, and that not without ſome griefe, the great loſſe that commeth to thoſe of my Companie and others, by errors or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily committed in meaſuring of timber; I did often thinke with my ſelfe what might be the readieſt courſe to redreſſe them. One while I thought to haue declared to you the Maſter and Wardens, what errors I had obſerued in our ordinarie meaſure, and ſo to haue deſired you in all dutie to haue prouided a remedie. But when I perceiued, that cuſtome had cauſed error to be receiued as a truth, and that therefore men would not forſake them, vnleſſe they were plainly conuinced to haue erred: And when I did alſo ſee, that moſt men are very ignorant in true meaſure, though they ſeeme and profeſſe to know much therein; and did alſo remember that not only Carpenters in this Citie doe in this ſort erre, but alſo Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters elſewhere, as alſo Shipwrights &amp; others, and that throughout the whole land, for the moſt part: then this courſe ſeemed to me to be too priuate, and ſuch as was like to doe but little good. The beſt courſe that I could thinke vpon, was, to publiſh ſome booke, wherein not onely true meaſure ſhould be ſet downe, but alſo the common errors plainly laid open to the capacitie of the ſimpleſt; that ſo all men might take knowledge thereof.</p>
            <p>My ſelfe I knew to be very vnfit for this worke, both becauſe of mine inabilitie, as alſo by reaſon of ſome exceptions that diuers
<pb facs="tcp:2036:4"/>might take againſt me, to their owne hindrance and my diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But when I ſaw none addreſſed hereunto then (remembring the ſaying of a Heathen, <hi>that men are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for themſelues, but for their Countrey</hi>) I did ſet aſide all lets, and both boldly and rudely haue put out this my ſimple booke, in manner as you ſee.</p>
            <p>The booke I haue diuided into three parts. In the firſt part I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the errors moſt commonly committed, and taken for truth, in meaſuring of timber. In the ſecond part I ſhew how ordinarie timber may be meaſured, both by ſundrie plaine waies, as alſo by waies more artificiall. And in the third part I ſhew, how extraordinarie timber and ſollid formes may be meaſured.</p>
            <p>The errors ordinarily committed in meaſuring timber, are many. But of them all, eſpecially two, bringeth loſſe to the buyer. The firſt is by buying of waynie timber and meaſuring it as ſquare. The other is by taking halfe the breadth and thicknes of a peece being added together, for the ſquare thereof.</p>
            <p>Theſe errors are ſuch, as bring apparant dammage: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are not to be reſpected lightly. I would they might not bee ſaid to be a great cauſe, if not of the ouerthrow, yet of the impairing of ſome mens eſtates.</p>
            <p>For as for wainie timber, who knowes not, that as it is often mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured and hewed, a loade and a halfe will not goe ſo farre in vſe, as a loade of good timber being well hewed and iuſtly meaſured.</p>
            <p>And as for haluing the ſumme of the two ſides for the ſquare, the dammage hereby is exceeding much; not onely to thoſe that buy much Timber at the firſt hand, but alſo, and that eſpecially (which is the more pitie) to the poorer ſort that buy at the ſecond hand. For my ſelfe haue abated of that which workmen themſelues haue mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured a peece vnto by the foreſaid falſe way, after <hi>3, 4, 5,</hi> yea <hi>6</hi> foote of timber in <hi>20:</hi> and yet I haue giuen them no more then their meaſure.</p>
            <p>I cannot ſtand to amplifie theſe errors in this place: they are more fully ſet downe in the booke it ſelfe. By which (if they be well weighed and conſidered vpon) it will plainly appeare to be true as I haue ſaid, namely, that there commeth great loſſe by the ordinarie meaſuring of timber.</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing the caſe ſo ſtands, my deſire and requeſt is, euen to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb facs="tcp:2036:4"/>man, but eſpecially to you the Master, Wardens, and Aſſiſtants of our Companie; that you would put your helping hand to reforme theſe errors. Many reaſons might be alleaged to induce you hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, but for ſome reaſons beſt knowne to my ſelfe, I omit them all, not doubting of your care and regard hereunto.</p>
            <p>I haue heard ſome men wiſh, that wee had an act of Parliament procured for redreſſe of falſe meaſure. But truly that ſeemeth to be the law of our land alreadie, though not the ſtatute law: for the law intendeth that the buyer ſhould haue that which he buyeth. And when we buy a loade of timber, doe we not intend that we haue bought <hi>50.</hi> foote of ſollid timber, euery foote being full <hi>12.</hi> inches euery way, that is, in length, breadth &amp; thicknes? Why then may we not require ſo much for a loade, and why is not the ſeller bound to deliuer it? And if a man that buyeth twentie buſhels of wheate, will not take ninteene; or if he buy a yard of cloath, he will not take three quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: Then why ſhould we (buying a loade of timber) take <hi>40.</hi> foote for it, yea and leſſe too (as oft times it fals out) whereas wee ſhould haue <hi>50.</hi> foote.</p>
            <p>I know that many men will obiect many things; and it is not for me at this time to refute them. Onely whereas ſome may ſay, that what is wanting in the meaſure, is allowed in the price. I anſwere: <hi>1.</hi> That is not alwaies. <hi>2.</hi> But where allowance is made, it is not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the value of the loſſe comming by the falſe meaſure. <hi>3.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, it is a preposterous courſe, to raiſe or let fall a price by altering of a ſet meaſure to an vncertaintie, whereas we vſe in all trades to raiſe or let fall the price according to the goodnes or badnes of the wares, keeping ſtil the ſame meaſure for them both. And ſurely here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we are but deceiued: For oft times we haue twelue pence bated in the price of a loade, and loſe foure or fiue ſhillings in the meaſure thereof.</p>
            <p>Therefore let vs either haue iuſt meaſure, if we buy by meaſure; or els let vs buy it by geſſe. For it is a ſhame to pretend to meaſure truly, and yet doe nothing leſſe.</p>
            <p>As touching my ſelfe, I deſire that my endeuour may be fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably accepted: for I write with no other mind then as tendring my Companies good. If any thing that I haue ſaid, be impugned as falſe, I will be readie whenſoeuer you will call me, to proue my affirmations.
<pb facs="tcp:2036:5"/>If any man of knowledge ſhall except againſt me, for my rude writing and groſſe demonstrations: I pray them to vnderſtand, that I writ not for them, but for the ſimple; and therfore I demonſtrate groſſely, not being well able to doe better: Alſo, that I am not a ſcholler but a Carpenter, and therefore could not but write rudely. Vnto ſuch alſo I doe further ſay, that my deſire is, that they would take knowledge, that this hath been one cauſe of my writing, euen to prouoke them (ſeeing our preſent error and loſſe, with which peraduenture they were not ſo well acquainted as my ſelfe) to take ſome paines to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the ſame, in better ſort then either I haue or can doe.</p>
            <p>While this booke was in printing I came to the ſight of a Ruler, ſometimes inuented by one Maſter <hi>Bedwel;</hi> which as it is eaſie, ſo it is moſt ſpeedie, and not leſſe certaine (being truly made) for the meaſuring of timber and boord; which I expect and hope will be ſhortly publiſhed for the common good. But I will not trouble you with more words. Onely let me put you in minde of this one thing: That in as much as nothing is more fit for Carpenters to make them readie, not only in meaſure but alſo in other things, then Geometrie: that therefore ſuch as are of reaſonable capacitie, would ſpend ſome part of their ſpare times to ſtudie the ſame, in ſome meaſure at the leaſt. For your furtherance herein, there are eſpeciall good helps, both by the Lecture at <hi>Greſham</hi> Colledge euery Thurſday in the Terme times (if you were but a little entered) as alſo by <hi>Euclides</hi> Elements of Geometrie, which the right Worſhipfull Sir <hi>Henry Billingſley</hi> Knight, to the great good of the Common-wealth, though to his own great trauell and charge, hath tranſlated and publiſhed in our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh tongue. But I am ouer tedious: I pray you accept of this my poore endeuour, as a fruit of my heartie good will to my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, and others whom it may concerne. If it take none effect, I ſhall be ſorrie: but if it doe any good, I haue enough for my labour.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>RICHARD MORE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2036:5"/>
            <head>THE FIRST PART OF THE CARPENTERS RVLE, ſhewing diuers groſſe errors, generallie <hi>committed by Carpenters and others in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring of Timber, ariſing from the Rule, and the vſe thereof.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER. 1. The error in the Rules, and the reaſon thereof.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hoſe that indeuour to amend things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, muſt firſt of all labour to proue the faults, eſpecially when the parties deceiued, are not yet perſwaded, that they are out of the way. And becauſe men little regarde to returne vnto the right, when they doe not perceiue that they are far in the wrong: I haue therefore thought good to ſpend this firſt part of my booke, in ſhewing and declaring, that great error is to too ordinarily committed (by the moſt part of Carpenters and others in and about London, and elſewhere) in meaſuring of timber.</p>
               <p>Theſe errors doe ariſe, either by meanes of the Rule or Ruler, with which they meaſure Timber; or elſe by the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>applying or vſing thereof. I meane, the ordinarie way of meaſuring Timber is very erronious. But firſt of the faults to be obſerued in the Ruler it ſelfe.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:2036:6"/>
               <p>The ordinarie Rule which Carpenters, Shipwrights, and others doe vſe to meaſure Timber withall, was inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and publiſhed by Maſter <hi>Leonard Digger.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Digges Tectoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con.</note> Now thoſe Rules that agrée with that booke are ſo true, as that I déeme them ouercurious that except againſt them; and they will ſerue truly to meaſure Timber withall. But the moſt which haue that kinde of meaſure on them which Maſter <hi>Digges</hi> deſcribeth, are very falſe. I meane, thoſe diuiſions or ſtrikes which are ſet on them for meaſuring of Boord and Timber, are not in their right places.</p>
               <p>And as thoſe ſtrikes and diuiſſons agrée not with the truth, ſo vpon diuers Rules you ſhall finde them to diſagrée one from another: Yea hardly ſhall you ſée two Rules that do euery where agrée. Neither is this error inſenſible, and ſo not to be reſpected; but apparantly groſſe, and therefore not to be tollerated. For my ſelfe haue ſéene ſome Rules that in ſome of their diuiſions haue erred from the truth and from one another, after the rate of ſixe foote in an hundreth of Boord, and after foure foote in a lode of Timber. Neither is this error rare and in ſome alone, but ſo generall, as that if a man would examine them, he ſhould be forced to ſay, that true Rules are very ſcant.</p>
               <p>If I were demaunded the cauſe of this fault or error in the Rule, I ſhould anſwer, that in mine opinion it ariſeth hence. Many will take vpon them to make Rules, who haue not Maſter <hi>Digges</hi> his booke to make them by; or if they haue it, vnderſtand it not, neither the ground from whence the Rule is made, by which they might examine the Rules which they make: which ground is ſet downe in the eleuenth and twelfth chapters of the ſecond part of this booke. But ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily men make them one by another, wherof hath growne the former error.</p>
               <p>Thus much for the Rule. Now ſhould follow to ſhew the errors in meaſuring Boord and Planke: But becauſe I haue obſerued no maine error in meaſuring of ordinarie planke or Boord (though great fault in buying of waynie
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2036:6"/>Boord, and meaſuring it as ſquare) which I ſpeake of in the next chapter following. I will therefore ſay nothing thereof now, but paſſe to errors in meaſuring of Timber.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 2. The great loſſe that commeth in buying of timber and Boord that is wainie, and meaſuring it as ſquare.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very man that buyeth Boord or Timber, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to haue for a foote as followeth, that is to ſay, in Boord twelue ynches in length; and twelue in breadth; and in timber, twelue ynches in length, twelue in bredth and twelue in thicknes. But who ſo buyeth Timber or Boord that is waynie, and taketh it as if it were not way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, hath not his meaſure for his monie, but farre leſſe. This is a great fault, and generall throughout the whole compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and amongſt others alſo; yea and apparantly knowne and noted by euery man, and yet not amended nor indeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be amended by any.</p>
               <p>This fault in Boord ſéemeth to come from careleſneſſe, and in Timber (as I take it) it did firſt grow from igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. For when men knew not now to meaſure a waynie péece of Timber, nor bow to deduct the waynes, hauing meaſured it as not waynie; then they did careleſly ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe this thing as a neceſſarie euill, or as an inconuenience that could not be auoyded.</p>
               <p>But it may be ſaid, that there is allowance in the price. I anſwere, what is it in a loade of Timber or in a perſell of Boord to haue twelue pence abated in the price, and to loſe foure or fiue ſhillings in the meaſure. This is to get in the hundreth and loſe in the Shire.</p>
               <p>And beſides this loſſe that commeth by waynie Timber, there is alſo another great loſſe thereby not to be forgotten. You know that when the Timber is very waynie, we are compelled to hew away a great part of it, after it is ſawed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2036:7"/>to bring it to ſome reaſonable ſquarenes fit for vſe. If then you ſhall put this loſſe to the other, you ſhall finde, that it is no ſmall damage that commeth by buying of waynie timber. And therefore there ſhould be an extraordinarie care and reſpect had to the meaſure, that we loſe not by it, ſéeing ſo great loſſe commeth by the ſtuffe it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>My deſire therefore is, that as other faults; ſo this may be amended. Not that I would haue Timber hewed dye ſquare, for that were a ſpoyle of much good Timber: nor that I would haue girt meaſure vſed, for that (in this kinde) is very falſe, as appeareth afterwards: But I would haue the want or wainyneſſe deducted or taken out of the whole péece; which how it may be don, is ſhewed in the ſecond part of this booke, Chapter 5.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 3. That it is very falſe, to take for the ſquare of a peece of Timber, the halfe of the breadth and thicknes, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded together: by which ſquare, ſhould be found the length of a foote in that peece.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a common practiſe, and that of ould, that who ſo of the ordinarie and common ſort of men, doe meaſure Timber, they take this courſe. Firſt they ad or put together the breadth and thickneſſe of the péece of Timber to be meaſured; then they take the halfe thereof for the ſquare of the ſame péece; and then according to that ſquare, they giue the length of a foote by the Rule. As for example, if the péece be ten ynches one way, and fourtéene ynches the other way, they ad together ten and fourtéene, which make twentie foure; the halfe of twentie foure is twelue, which (ſay they) is the ſquare of this péece of Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; which is very falſe. And yet this courſe is ſo generally receiued, and ſo commonly reputed and taken for good, as that he ſhall be thought ouercurious of ſome, that ſhall but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2036:7"/>except againſt it. Howbeit if you will but marke that which followeth, you ſhall plainely ſée that it is an error, and that a great one.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Thus then appeareth the error. If you will know the greatnes thereof, you ſhall vnderſtand, that in the former example, and ſo in all Timber that haue like differences of ſides as that péece hath, there is loſſe alwayes to the buyer, a quarter of that which he buyeth, or one loade of Timber in foure. If the difference of the ſides be ſmaller, then is the loſſe ſmaller: but if it be greater, then is the loſſe greater. And in generall take this for a rule. That there is loſt by this kinde of falſe meaſuring, a ſquare péece of Timber, as long as the whole péece to be meaſured, and as broade and thicke as halfe the difference of the two ſides of the ſaid péece of Timber to be meaſured. As for example, let the ſides be ten and fourtéene, then their difference is foure (for four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téene is more then ten, by foure) now the halfe of foure is two, which two is the ſide of the ſaid loſt ſquare péece of Timber throughout the péece.</p>
               <p>Now ſéeing this error of taking halfe the ſum of the ſides for the ſquare, is very manifeſt; and ſéeing alſo it is an error tending to the great loſſe of the buyer, yea to the loſſe of thrée loade in foure, and more alſo as the differences may be: Therefore I deſire that none would follow that corrupt cuſtome, and moſt falſe way; but ſuffer themſelues to be better inſtructed, in more righter wayes. Which if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to doe, and ſhall buy much Timber after that rate, their purſes are like to pay for it.</p>
               <p>But ſome may ſay vnto me, this fault is by diuers diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and a redreſſe not altogether vnthought of. I graunt, many doe ſée it, and doe indeuour to reforme it thus. If a péece of Timber bee eightéene ynches one way, and ſixe ynches the other way, they imagine it to conſiſt of thrée ſquares of ſixe ynches a péece (as indéede it doth) the which they meaſure ſeuerally, and then adde al their contents together, which they take for the meaſure of the whole péece.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:2036:8"/>
               <p>This is true both in this example, and in all others that will fall out in any number of iuſt ſquares. But when the ſides of the Timber to be meaſured, haue not this anſwere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ablenes in them, as nine ynches one way and fourtéene the other way; or ſeauen and nintéene, or ſuch like: then they are to ſéeke. For when they haue taken the thicknes out of the breadth as often as they may, then is the remainder vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquare: In meaſuring whereof, they faile and erre, as a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; and yet they profeſſe, not to regard it. For (ſay they) if the difference of the ſides be not paſt thrée or foure ynches, that péece may be meaſured according to the ſaid erronious way, and no great loſſe happen thereby. But what the loſſe is, I haue ſhewed before, which although it ſéeme but ſmall, yet in time it ariſeth to no ſmall matter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 4. The error in meaſuring of timber not hewed ſquare but beuell.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough this error be not of any great moment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Timber hewed beuell or ſkew, commeth not often to be meaſured: yet becauſe ſometimes there is ſuch Timber to be ſould, I would not haue workemen to be ignorant, that it is an apparant error to meaſure it, as if it were hewed ſquare.</p>
               <p>When the corners of the Timber are hewed vnſquare; I doe not meane waynie; for of that I haue ſpoken before in the ſecond chapter: but when it is hewed beuell or diamond wiſe (as ſometimes it is by the careleſneſſe or vnſkilfulnes of the hewer) then to take the ſquare of ſuch Timber, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the breadth of the ſides thereof, is vntrue; for the ſides are longer then if it were ſquare, and ſo giues the péece to be bigger then it is.</p>
               <p>How great this error is, I ſtand not to ſhew at this time: Only note that it doth increaſe and decreaſe according as the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2036:9"/>corners of the Timber doe ſwarue from ſquare. But how ſuch Timber is to be meaſured, ſée in the third part, Chapter ſhe ſixt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 5. The error in the ordinarie meaſuring of round Timber.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He former errors doe alwayes bring loſſe to the buyer, but theſe that follow doe alwayes bring loſſe to the ſeller. And though ſuch round Timber commeth not often to be meaſured here in London (the worſe for the buyer) yet would I haue Carpenters know the error which is vſed in meaſuring the ſame; which is this.</p>
               <p>They girt the Timber rounde about with a line or thread, and then take one quarter thereof for the ſquare (as we call it) of the péece to be meaſured, and ſo finde out (as they thinke) the length of a foote in that péece of Timber or trée.</p>
               <p>This is a groſſe error, and yéeldeth not the content of the péece or trée, by one fift part of it and more.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>But how round Timber is to be meaſured is taught in the ſixt chapter of the ſecond part, and in the ninth chapter of the third part of this booke: which when you haue learned and tryed, then you will tell your ſelfe, that in meaſuring round Timber after the former way, is very erronious and intolerable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 5. Error in meaſuring of Timber not fully round, but ſomewhat flat called Ouall faſhion.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>So that to meaſure Ouals by the former way, is ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine, that you may haue peraduenture more then you ſhould, and peraduenture leſſe then you ſhould by a fift part, a fourth part, a third part, and ſo forth. But becauſe (ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily) trées or Timber that are Duall faſhion, doe not much vary from a round: Therefore the loſſe is alwayes to the ſeller, being meaſured as a foreſaid.</p>
               <p>Here I had purpoſed to haue ſomewhat digreſſed from my generall purpoſe, and to haue ſhewed the great loſſe that commeth by buying of fagots that are bound flat: But the Statute for fewell in the laſt Parliament hath preuented me: Where it is enacted, that bands of fagots ſhall be <hi>Round.</hi> But yet becauſe I feare al men vnderſtand not what is ment by the word <hi>Round,</hi> or if they doe, yet they will not regarde to redreſſe it: I pray you therefore take knowledge, that where as men doe commonly buy the flatteſt fagots for the greateſt, they are deceiued; for indéede they are leſſe then the round by farre; and euermore the flatter they are, the leſſer they are. And to ſpeake no more then my ſelfe haue tryed; I haue taken foure fagots (indéede of the flatteſt) and haue put the wood of them all into thrée of their owne bands without ſtrayning. Lo then the great loſſe that comes to folke by this error. That which I ſay of fagots I intend alſo to be ſpoken of billets: For the flatter they are, the leſſer they are, being no more in compaſſe then the ſtatute re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires.</p>
               <p>I néede not ſtand to demonſtrate that this is an error, if I were perſwaded you vnderſtood that which is ſaid before of Ouals. But for farther proofe, take a quarte pot of peuter that is round, and make it more flat by cruſhing in the ſides thereof; and you ſhall finde that it will not hold a quart of water as before it did, and yet the compaſſe of the pot is as much as it was before. You may alſo proue the ſame by a Boord thus. The fagot band ought to be by the Statute
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2036:10"/>twentie foure ynches about: So then a Boordes end of a foote broad will hardly goe into one of thoſe bands; but if you cleaue that Boordes end into a doſen or more péeces; you ſhall well perceiue that you may put foure and more of ſuch Boordes being ſo cleſt, into that band being round. This haue I written, not carpingly, but as deſierous that the buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers would not deceiue themſelues by their eye, neither that they ſhould be deceiued by others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 7. The error in meaſuring timber that is waynie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Told you before in the ſecond chapter, that there comes great loſſe to Carpenters in buying of way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie Timber after the ordinarie way: But here I ſhew the loſſe that comes (indéede not to the buyer but the ſeller) in meaſuring of waynie Timber.</p>
               <p>It hath béen vſed (as I am informed) that if Timber were waynie, the buyer would meaſure it as by girting it about, and taking one quarter of the comqaſſe for the ſquare, as in the caſe of round Timber before ſhewed, chapter the ſixth. But it ſéemeth to me, that the ſeller grew wearie of this way, ſo that in my time to my knowledge, it hath not béen vſed in or about this Citie.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>How much this loſſe is, doth not appeare by this demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration. But in this figure (if you will take my word) there is loſt a ſixt part full. But I had rather you would trie the loſſe your ſelues, by the rule taught in the fift chapter of the ſecond part of this booke, then to beleeue me in this caſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 8. That in meaſuring of Timber that is taper growne, it is falſe to take the ſquare of the middle thereof, and ſo to giue vp the content by the common Rule.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is ſo vſuall a thing in meaſuring of Timber that is taper growne, or narrower at one end then at another, to take the ſquare of the middle of the péece, and ſo to meaſure it by the common Rule; as that I ſhall be not onely not beléeued, but alſo reputed to haue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parantly erred in affirming the contrary: for it will be ſaid, that that which it hath too much in the greater halfe, it wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the leſſer halfe. Indéede this is true in Boords or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuperficies that taper, whoſe ſides are ſtraight: but in a ſolid or péece of Timber it is ſimply falſe.</p>
               <p>How to demonſtrate the error on a paper, ſo as that it may be eaſily conceiued, is very hard: but in a ſolid it may plainely be declared to the vnderſtanding of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſt.</p>
               <p>If a Pyramis (that is, a pyked péece of Timber, ſharpe at one end, like a pyked ſtéeple) were ſo meaſured, there would be loſt very much. And alwayes the leſſer the péece doth taper, the leſſer is the loſſe. In generall, there is loſt, (by certaine pyramides) a péece of Timber whoſe length is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2036:11"/>the ſixt part of the length of the whole péece, and whoſe end or baſe is contained vnder halfe the difference of the ſides of both the ends of ſuch a tapered péece: that is, take for the breadth of the loſt péce, halfe the difference of the breadth of both ends; and for the thicknes of the loſt péce, halfe the difference of the thicknes of both ends. As for example, if the péece be twentie ynches broad and ſixtéene ynches thicke at one end, and fiftéene ynches broade, and twelue ynches thicke at the other end, and twentie foure foot long: then the laſt péece is foure foote long, two ynches and a halfe broade, and two ynches thick: for two and a halfe is the halfe of fiue, which is the difference of the breadth of both ends; and two is the halfe of foure, which is the difference of the thicknes of both ends.</p>
               <p>The loſſe that commeth by this error is to the ſeller: and yet in truth it is ſuch as yéeldeth no profit to the buyer. For we loſe more by ſuch Timber, being imployed to any ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie vſe, then that aduantage by the meaſure doth come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. But yet I would not haue workemen to take that way for a true meaſure which is falſe; neither to be ignorant how ſuch Timber is to be meaſured, if occaſion doe offer, or if men ſhall require it.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond and third part of this booke, where I ſhew how to meaſure Timber, I will ſhew how tapered Timber may be meaſured: from which I will no longer detaine you, taking that to be ſufficient which I haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten alreadie, to ſhew the groſſeſt of the errors, generally committed by Carpenters and others, in meaſuring of Timber.</p>
               <trailer>The end of the firſt part.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:2036:12"/>
            <head>THE SECOND PART OF THE CARPENTERS RVLE, Wherein is ſet downe ſundrie plaine <hi>wayes, truly to meaſure ordinarie Timber, and Boord.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER. 1. How Boords and planks are ordinarily meaſured.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the former part of this booke, I told you that I had not obſerued any maine error in <hi>meaſuring</hi> of ordinarie Boord and planke, though great fault in <hi>buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of wainie boord and planke, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring it as ſquare: And therefore it ſhall not be needefull to inuent or ſet downe any new wayes of meaſuring of them: onely it ſhall ſuffice to repeate the wayes alreadie in vſe ordinarily, which are thrée. Of which, the firſt is troubleſome, and therefore ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be knowne for varietie, then vſed in meaſuring. The ſecond is true, but longer in doing then the third; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I would aduiſe the third to be followed and vſed. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly looke that your Rule be truely made, and that diligence be vſed in meaſuring therewith: elſe there will follow error of neceſſitie, bee the wayes to meaſure by, neuer ſo exact.
<note place="margin">The firſt way to meaſure boord.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt way let be this. And firſt note that for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, I call an ynch that which is an inch broad and twelue
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2036:12"/>ynches long, of which ynches, twelue doe make a foote. Now if the Boord to be meaſured be vnder a foote in breadth, then reckon how many times twelue of the ſaid ynches you can haue in the whole Boord, and ſo many foote is there in it. If the Boord be iuſt a foote broade, then it containes ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny foote as it is féete in length. But if it be more then a foote broad; then meaſure it as a foreſaid as if it were two Boords, the one of a foote broade, the other ſo broad as the odde inches remaining: then adde their contents together for the content of the whole boord.</p>
               <p>This rule, to them that vnderſtand it, may be fitlier ſet downe in other words thus. Multiplie the number of inches in the breadth, by the number of feete in the length: then di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide the product by twelue, and the quotient ſhewes the number of féete in the boord.</p>
               <p>The ſecond way is thus, Meaſure the length of the boord:
<note place="margin">The ſecond way to meaſure boord.</note> Then (if the ſame boord be vnder a foote brode) draw or ſet the breadth thereof ſo many times on the boord, as it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ntayneth féete in length, and there make a pricke: And then ſo many foote as there are from the beginning to that pricke, ſo many foote doth the boord contayne.</p>
               <p>And if the boord be aboue a foote broade, then you may take out the euen féete, and meaſure the remainder as aforeſaid; and then adde both thoſe together for the content of the whole.</p>
               <p>The third way, is this. Take the breadth of the boord;
<note place="margin">The third way to meaſure boord.</note> then finde by the Rule what length, maketh a foote, at that breadth; and then ſée how many times that length is in the boord, and ſo many foote are in it. Theſe I ſtand not vpon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are well enough knowne to all men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:2036:13"/>
               <head>CHAP. 2. How to meaſure Timber by a certaine way called Drawght-meaſure.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His way may fall out ſo tedious, as that I would not haue troubled either my ſelfe to write it, or you to reade it, had it not béen that I would not haue you ignorant of that way which ſome doe vſe in ſome places of this Land. The way is thus.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>This rule aforeſaid will hold true for any Timber that is vnder a foote ſquare. But if it be aboue a foote ſquare, and not aboue two foote ſquare; then muſt you imagine that one quarter thereof is to be meaſured (and therefore take but halfe of each of the two ſides) and when you haue ſo caſt it vp as if it were but a quarter, accoumpt foure times ſo much for the content of the whole péece.</p>
               <p>But if the péece of Timber be aboue two foote ſquare, and not aboue foure foote ſquare; then may you imagine that a ſixtéenth part thereof is to be meaſured. Which done, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coumpt ſixtéene times ſomuch for the content of the whole péece: now to take the ſixtéenth part, you may take a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the breadth, and a quarter of the thicknes.</p>
               <p>But this kinde of meaſure if it fall out in a péece of Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber aboue a foote ſquare is ſo tedious, as that I doe wonder any man would content himſelfe with it. And yet becauſe I haue ſet it downe, take one note more, which is this. If the péece to be meaſured haue any od ynches in the length, either at the firſt or ſecond working: then muſt you, hauing drawne the want ſo many times as there is féete in length, adde thereunto ſuch part of the want, as the od meaſure of the length is part of a foote. And thus much of Drawght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:2036:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. 3. How Timber may be meaſured by Boord meaſure onely.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I conſidered the readines of many men in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring of boord by one of the thrée former wayes, and how ſpéedily they will caſt vp the whole ſtocke hauing meaſured one boord, by the obſeruing of ſkores, tens, and fiues therein; and withall conſidering the great error that thoſe men run into in meaſuring of Timber: This mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me to thinke of ſome courſe, how theſe men that are ſo expert in meaſuring of boord, might by the ſame way meaſure any ſquare péece of Timber.</p>
               <p>This way, though it be true, yet it is troubleſome; and therefore I would wiſh them rather to vſe ſome of the wayes following: But if their readines in caſting vp a ſtocke of boords ſhall cauſe them to accept of this way, I will not be their let. Now the way is this.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe the péece of Timber (to be meaſured) to be a ſtocke of boordes, conſiſting of ſo many boordes as there be inches in the thicknes of the péece. Then meaſure one of thoſe ſuppoſed boordes: that done, caſt vp the whole ſtocke. Now this being performed, you are to know that euery twelue foote of boord is a foote of Timber, as euery man may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue; and ſixe foote of boord is halfe a foote of Timber; and thrée foote, is a quarter of a foote of timber. Alſo, euery thrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſkore foote of boord is fiue foote of Timber, and ſo, ſixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſkore foote of boord is ten foote of Timber, nineſkore foote of boord is fiftéene foote of Timber, twelueſkore is twentie foote, fiftéeneſkore or thrée hundreth, is twentie and fiue foote, ſixe hundreth foote of boord is fiftie foote of Timber, and ſo foorth. Now if this be obſerued, it is eaſie for any man to caſt vp the content of any ordinarie péece of Timber truly.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:2036:14"/>
               <p>There is farther to be noted, that if there be any od halfe ynches in the thicknes of the péece to be meaſured, that then it be accoumpted as halfe of one of the ſuppoſed boordes of the ſtocke: And if there be a quarter of one inch, then it is a quarter of a boord: And if there be an od thrée quarters of an inch, it is thrée quarters of a boord; and if there be any other od part of an inch, it is the ſame part of a boord, and muſt be counted with the whole ſtocke.</p>
               <p>This way is ſo plaine that it néedeth no example. I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the ſimpleſt may vnderſtand it, and therefore I will ſay no more of it: Onely this you may obſerue, that you may meaſure the péece, by imagining it to be diuided into two inch, thrée inch, or foure inch planke; ſo that you ſearch out how many foote of ſuch planke is contayned in a foote of Timber.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 4. How Timber may be meaſured after the ordinarie way, by deducting the loſt ſquare.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was obſerued in the third chapter of the firſt part of this booke, that when any péece of Timber is meaſured after the moſt common way, which is by adding the breadth and thicknes together, and taking the halfe thereof for the ſquare of the péece, &amp;c. that then there is alwayes loſt a ſquare péece of Timber of the whole length of the péece to be meaſured, whoſe ſquare is halfe the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the two ſides of the péece. Now by obſeruing of this loſt ſquare, any ordinarie péece of Timber may be truly mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured as followeth.</p>
               <p>Meaſure the péece, by taking for the ſquare thereof, the halfe of the ſumme or totall of the two ſides, as is aforeſaid, and as is vſually accuſtomed. This done, note the difference of the two ſides: then take the halfe of that difference for the ſide of the loſt ſquare, which is all the length of the péece.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2036:15"/>Then meaſure that ſuppoſed or loſt ſquare, and what it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounteth vnto, deduct out of the meaſure of the whole péece being meaſured after the ſaid common way, and the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is the true content of the péece.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>And becauſe the loſt ſquare may haue in it an odde halfe inch, as ſome times it hath, as thrée inches and ahalfe or ſuch like: I haue therefore added vnto the common rule, what length maketh a foote of Timber from an inch to ten inches, noting ſtill euery halfe inch: As you may behold in the table of Timber meaſure hereafter following in the latter ende of this ſecond part. For to take halfe the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2036:15"/>difference betwixt the two next adioyning numbers of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches added to the leſſer of them (as commonly men doe) is not true: As for example; at an inch ſquare one hundred forty foure foote in length maketh a foote of timber: at two inches, thirtie ſix foote doth it: ſo that if the halfe betwixt thirtie ſixe and one hundred and forty foure were taken and added to thirtie ſixe for the length of a foote at an inch and a halfe ſquare, it would be nintie foote, whereas in truth it is but ſixtie foure foote: ſo in this example it erreth twentie ſixe foote in length of a péece of Timber of an inch and a halfe ſquare. And how ſo euer it be not ſo much in other numbers aboue two inches ſquare, yet it alwayes erreth more or leſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 5. How wainie or canted Timber may be meaſured.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough there be diuers wayes to meaſure wainie or canted Timber, yet I will obſerue onely this one plaine way. Meaſure then the péece as if it were not wainie, out of which deduct the waines, and the remainder is the true content of the péece.</p>
               <p>How to deduct the waines is better taught by an example then by a precept: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuppoſe the figure <hi>A</hi> were the ende of a péece of Timber of ten inches ſquare, hauing one corner thereof wainie: this péece meaſure as if it were not wainie. That done, meaſure what the waine is either way from the corners, which I call the wants, becauſe the péece
<figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure> wanteth ſo much of ſquare; which want in this example is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2036:16"/>foure inches either way, as you may ſée by the two prickt lines with the figure of foure ſtanding by either of them. This meaſure as if it were a péece of Timber of foure inches either way, and as long as the whole péece. That done take halfe the content thereof; the which halfe deduct out of the meaſure of the whole péece as it was before meaſured; and the remainder will be the true content thereof. And as you doe with this corner, ſo muſt you doe with the reſt, if they be wainie alſo.</p>
               <p>And here I would haue you note, that where I bid the halfe of the content of the ſaid ſquare to be deducted, that the reaſon hereof is, for that in Geometry, all paralletograms and parallelipipidons, are deuided into two equall partes by their diameters, as it is demonſtrated in <hi>Euclide, booke, 1. propoſition 34. and booke 11. propoſition 18.</hi> That is to ſay in playner termes for our purpoſe, a boord or a péece of Timber which haue their oppoſite or contrarie ſides equally diſtant, being cut into two péeces by a ſtraight line paſſing by the oppoſite corners, as you may ſée in the figure B, I ſay, that boord or péece of Timber, is cut into two equall parts. So that it is manifeſt by this,
<figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure> that the ſaid waine is halfe ſo much as the péece whoſe ſides are equall to the ſaid wants.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 6. How round Timber may be meaſured.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Told you before, that I would not trouble you with Geometricall workes. And howſoeuer I doe hereafter ſet downe ſome more artificiall wayes to meaſure by, yet my indeauor eſpecially is to correct the common errors by that knowledge which moſt men haue
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2036:16"/>alreadie: and therefore you may meaſure round Timber plainly in this ſort. Girt the piece about with a line or thred: then take a quarter thereof for the ſquare of that piece, (though indeede it be not the ſquare) and ſo meaſure it after the common way. But now, note that which I told you in the firſt part of this booke, namely that this piece is more then it is thus meaſured to be.
<note place="margin">See a more exact way in the third part of this book, chap. the 10.</note> And therefore to finde the true content, adde to that which you haue meaſured the piece to be, a quarter thereof, and alſo after the rate of a foote in a loade, and then the totall will ſhew the content of the piece, though not exactly, yet ſo neere, as that the loſſe will not bring any dammage to any man, that is worth looking after.</p>
               <p>Take an example for more plainnes. Suppoſe the tree be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing meaſured after the former way to containe twentie foot: then muſt you adde thereto a quarter thereof which is 5, and that makes <hi>25</hi> foote. Then adde to that, halfe a foote, which is after a foote in a loade, and the content of the piece will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to <hi>25</hi> foote and a halfe.</p>
               <p>And here is to be noted, that if the piece bee not exactly round, that then this meaſure will not hold, as was ſhewed in the ſeuenth Chapter of the former part of this booke. But how ſuch Timber is to be meaſured, ſee in the latter end of the eleuenth Chapter of the third part.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 7. How Timber may be meaſured by Arithmeticke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough the former waies for meaſuring of Timber be ſufficient, yet becauſe varietie giueth pleaſure, and theſe that follow admit of leſſe error in the working then ſome of the former, I haue therefore thought good to ſet them downe as followeth. And if any man ſhall obiect that I ſpend this labour in vaine, becauſe Carpenters commonly haue not Arithmetick. I anſwere, that ſome haue
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2036:17"/>more knowledge therin, then they know how to applie to the preſent purpoſe; for whom chiefly I haue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this chapter and ſome others following: as alſo I could wiſh that others which haue not, would learne; which they may do by bookes which are extant: or at leaſt forbeare to be common Rule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, vntill they haue knowledge therein, or well vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the tables which are for that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Here firſt I ſhould haue ſhewed how to meaſure boord by Arithmeticke: but becauſe it little differeth from meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of paralellograms, I will therfore referre it to the third part of this booke, where it is taught how to meaſure them.</p>
               <p>Now to meaſure Timber by Arithmeticke, doe thus. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the length of the piece to be meaſured into inches, by multiplying the number of féet therein contained by twelue. Then multiplie the breadth by the thicknes, and the product or ſumme thereof multiplie by the length, being alſo reduced into inches, as aforeſaid. Then diuide that product or of come by <hi>1728</hi> (which is the number of inches in a foote of timber) and the quotient will giue you the number of feete contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in that piece of timber.</p>
               <p>Here it ſhall not be vnneceſſarie to giue two examples; the one where the lengeth, breadth and thicknes are euen inches; and the other, where they haue odde parts of an inch.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe the piece of timber to be meaſured to be nine foote in length, eightéene inches in breadth, and ſixe inches in thicknes. Now multiplie nine foote the length by twelue, and that yéelds <hi>108.</hi> inches, which being multiplied by <hi>18.</hi> the breadth, makes <hi>1944.</hi> and that being multiplied by ſixe the thicknes, yéeldeth <hi>11664.</hi> which is the content of the whole piece in inches. Then diuide this <hi>11664.</hi> by <hi>1728.</hi> and the quotient will be ſixe foote and <hi>1296/1728</hi> parts of a foote, which being reduced to his loweſt denomination, is <hi>¾</hi> of a foot. So that the whole piece is ſixe foote and three quarters. And if you would know how many quarters of a foote is in any ſuch fraction, you may diuide it by <hi>432</hi> the number of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in a quarter of a foote of timber, &amp; the quotient will tell
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2036:17"/>you. But ſuppoſe the piece haue in the breadth or thicknes, an od quarter, or halfe, or thrée quarters of an inch: then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the length, breadth and thicknes into quarters of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: after that, multiplie them being ſo reduced one into another, that is, the length by the breadth, and that of come or product by the thicknes. Then diuide that totall by <hi>110592</hi> (which is the number of quarters of inches contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in a foote of timber) and the quotient will ſhew you how many foote is contained in the piece. As for example, let the piece be <hi>20</hi> foote long, <hi>8</hi> inches and a halfe broad, and <hi>11</hi> inches and three quarters thicke: Firſt I reduce <hi>20</hi> foote the length into quarters of inches by multiplying <hi>20</hi> by <hi>12,</hi> which is <hi>240,</hi> which brings <hi>20</hi> foote into inches: then I mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplie that <hi>240</hi> by <hi>4,</hi> to bring them into quarters of inches, which is <hi>960.</hi> Secondly, reduce <hi>8</hi> inches and a halfe the breadth, into quarters of inches, which is <hi>34.</hi> Thirdly, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce <hi>11.</hi> inches and thrée quarters the thicknes into quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of inches, which is <hi>47.</hi> Then multiplie <hi>960,</hi> and <hi>34,</hi> and <hi>47,</hi> together, and they make <hi>1534080.</hi> Laſtly, diuide theſe by <hi>110592,</hi> and the quotient will be <hi>13,</hi> and <hi>96384</hi> odde quarters of inches: which being diuided by <hi>27648,</hi> the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of quarters of an inch in a quarter
<note n="*" place="margin">Note here that I mean not by a quarter of a foote, a ſquare of 3. inches, which is a quarter of a foote one way: but the fourth part of a ſquare foot of timber.</note> of a foot of timber, the quotient will be three quarters of a foote, and ſomewhat more, but it is not to be regarded in a whole piece of timber: ſo that the content of the piece is <hi>13</hi> foote, three quarters of a foote and ſomewhat more. This is more tedious to teach then to practiſe. Behold the worke on the other ſide of the leafe.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:2036:18"/>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="math">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>Note, that where there is no odde parts of an inch in the breadth or thicknes, then you may more briefly caſt vp the content thus: Multiplie the number of inches in the breadth by the number of inches in the thicknes, and the product thereof multiplie by the number of féete in the length. Then diuide that totall by <hi>144,</hi> and the quotient will giue the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the péece in feete. As in the firſt example behold.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="math">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:2036:18"/>
               <head>CHAP. 8. A ſecond way how Timber may be meaſured by Arithmetick.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltiplie the breadth in the thicknes, and by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct or ofcome thereof diuide <hi>1728,</hi> and the quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient will ſhew you how much in length maketh a foote of that piece; according to which you muſt meaſure the whole piece. And if there be any odde quarters, or halfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the breadth or thicknes, then reduce the two ſides in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to quarters of inches, as is taught in the laſt Chapter. Then hauing reduced them, multiplie the breadth by the thicknes, and by their product diuide <hi>27648.</hi> and the quotient ſhewes you the length of the foote in inches, which you may bring into féete by diuiding them by <hi>12.</hi> Behold an example of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kind in the worke following.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Example</hi> 1. <gap reason="math">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Example</hi> 2. <gap reason="math">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:2036:19"/>
               <p>And if you would know how many quarters of an inch any fraction of an inch doth containe: or for example, how many quarters of an inch either of the ſaid fractions of <hi>160/224</hi> and <hi>382/1598</hi> doe amount vnto, you néede but diuide their nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merators by a quarter of their denominators, or the product of the numerator being multiplied by <hi>4,</hi> by all their denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators, and either quotient is your deſire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 9. How Timber of vnequall ſides, may, by Arithmetick, be brought into a ſquare, and ſo meaſured by the common way.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Aſter <hi>Digs</hi> in his Tectonicon made a Table of Squares, or a table to ſhew the ſquares of any ordinarie péece of timber of vnequall ſides, that ſo they might thereby truly meaſure the péece according to the Rule. Herein Maſter <hi>Digs</hi> took great paines, worthie to be commended. But men being loth to carrie a table in their pockets for trouble (as it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnto me) did altogether leaue it, and framed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the ſaid falſe way of haluing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſumme of the two ſides for the ſquare, which turned to the great loſſe of the buyers. Now my deſire is, that ſeeing men will not vſe that Table becauſe of trouble, that they would learne to carrie the ground thereof in their heads, which is contained in this Chapter. Wherein though there be ſome greater meaſure of Arithmetick required then in the former, namely extraction of the ſquare roote, yet the fruite of that kind of Arithmetick will repay any mans trauaile, that either hath, or will take paines to learne it.</p>
               <p>But to performe the queſtion, doe thus: Multiplie the breadth and thicknes of the péece together. Then take the ſquare roote of the product thereof, which ſquare roote is (as we call it) the ſquare of that péece, Then hauing the ſquare
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2036:19"/>giuen, you are not ignorant how to meaſure the péece by the rule. As for example: if the péece be <hi>16</hi> inches broade and <hi>4</hi> inches thicke: you muſt multiply <hi>16</hi> by <hi>4,</hi> which makes <hi>64.</hi> the ſquare roote whereof is <hi>8</hi> (for <hi>8</hi> times <hi>8</hi> is <hi>64.</hi>) Therefore <hi>8</hi> is the ſquare of that péece, and not <hi>10</hi> as your common way tels you.</p>
               <p>If the roote cannot be exactly extracted, as oftentimes it cannot, take the néereſt that you can, and which you ſhall thinke requiſit, by ſuch wayes as are alreadie extant in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers authors.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 10. A ſecond way to finde the ſquare of an vnequall ſided peece of Timber, namely, by the Scale and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecauſe this way is more eaſie and ſpéedie then the former, and that which may alſo be done by thoſe that haue no Arithmeticke: therefore I haue added this vnto the other.</p>
               <p>What is meant by the compaſſe, that is, a paire of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, all men know: but what is meant by the terme Scale, many peraduenture are ignorant of: therefore it ſhall not be vnneceſſarie to deſcribe it, as in this manner.</p>
               <p>A Scale is any line (and in ordinarie matters, any right line) diuided into any number of equall parts, be they great ter or leſſer, wider or narrower, of the diſtance of an inch-halfe ynch, quarter, halfe quarter, or any other diſtance grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or leſſer. This line thus diuided, is, I ſay, called a Scale; whereof euery part or diuiſion may ſtand for a mile, a rod, a yard, a foote, an inch, or any other kinde of meaſure what you will, or haue vſe of.</p>
               <p>But to the matter. On the backe-ſide of the Rule (as we call it) there is (you know) a voide roome or place, about the middell thereof. Now in this voyde place, draw a line, as
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2036:20"/>néere to the edge of the Rule as conueniently you can, ſome ſixe or ſeauen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches long, as here I haue drawne the line <hi>AB.</hi> Then from it, (and not from the edge of the Rule) and at the bottom of it, draw an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other line thwart or croſſe the Rule, which ſhall ſtand ſquare or perpendicular to the former line, as is this line <hi>BC.</hi> Then muſt theſe two lines of <hi>AB</hi> and <hi>BC</hi> be diuided into quarters of inches, beginning from the angle or corner at <hi>B:</hi> and euery one of thoſe quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of inches, diuide into foure equall portions or diuiſions, as here I haue diuided them.</p>
               <p>Here I pray you note once for all, that I call all thoſe quarters of inches, <hi>Parts</hi> of the Scale: euery one of which parts in this matter, is, or ſtandeth for an inch; and halfe a part is halfe an inch; a quarter of a part is a quarter of an inch; three quarters of a part is thrée quarters of an inch, and ſo forth. This done, your Scale is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of ruler</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:2036:20"/>
               <p>Now to finde the ſquare of any péece of Timber: firſt adde the breadth and thicknes together. That done, note the halfe thereof:
<note place="margin">Or, (which is all one) note what either of the two ſides doth differ from the ſaid halfe of the ſum of both ſides.</note> note alſo what is halfe the difference of the two ſides of the péece. Then reckoning how many inches and what od quarters of an inch there is in the ſaid halfe of both the ſides added together, you muſt open your conpaſſes (being ſmall or ſharpe in the points) to ſo many parts and ſuch od quarters of a part in the Scale. That don, ſet one foote of the compaſſes being ſo opened, vpon the line <hi>BC,</hi> ſo many parts and od quarters of a part from <hi>B,</hi> as there be inches and od quarters of an inch in halfe the difference of the ſides: And extend the other foote of the compaſſe vpon the line <hi>AB,</hi> and note where it cuts it, or lights vpon it. Now I ſay, that ſo many parts and od quarters of a part of the ſaid line <hi>AB,</hi> as are from <hi>B</hi> to the place where the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes did cut or light, ſo many inches and od quarters of an inch is there in the ſquare of the péece.</p>
               <p>This is far ſooner wrought then ſpoken, and is better ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained by an example, then taught by a rule. Therefore ſuppoſe the péece to be meaſured, be <hi>7</hi> inches one way, and <hi>11</hi> inches and a halfe the other way. Firſt I adde <hi>7</hi> to <hi>11 ½,</hi> which makes <hi>18 ½.</hi> Then I note the halfe thereof, which is <hi>9¼.</hi> I note alſo halfe the difference of the two ſides, which is two and <hi>¼.</hi> Laſtly I open my compaſſes as wide as nine parts and one quarter of a part, and ſet one foote at <hi>D,</hi> which is two parts and <hi>¼</hi> from <hi>B,</hi> and I extend the other foote to the line <hi>AB,</hi> and it cuts or lights at the point <hi>E.</hi> Then I ſay that the ſquare of that péece, is very néere nine inches, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are from <hi>B</hi> to Calmoſt nine parts.</p>
               <p>And here note,
<note place="margin">Note.</note> that whereas I ſuppoſe the Scale to be quarters of inches, you may make them to be halfe quarters of inches. And truly where the lines <hi>AB</hi> or <hi>BC</hi> will not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit or receiue all the inches they ſhould (which yet I thinke will rarely happen) then you muſt take for your Scale, halfe quarters of inches, and ſo procéede (as is before ſhewed) as if it were of quarters of inches.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:2036:21"/>
               <p>Note alſo that this Scale may as fitly be made on your ſquire; or elſe on the foreſide of the Rule, taking for the line <hi>AB,</hi> the line next to the edge of the Rule, as it is commonly diuided into quarters of inches, without any ſubdiuiſions into foure, for you may well enough gueſſe at them without any error to be reſpected: take alſo for the line <hi>BC,</hi> any one of the thwart ſtrokes which ſerues to diuide the Rule into inches (for I ſuppoſe them to ſtand ſquare to the ſaid other line;) which thwart ſtroke you muſt alſo diuide into quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of inches, as before is taught. And thus if one of the thwart ſtrokes ſhould be worne out with pricking (which will not be in ſhort time, if you worke lightly and with ſmall pointed compaſſes) then you may take another of the thwart ſtrokes, and diuide it into quarters, and ſo procéede as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 11. How that meaſure which is called boord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſure is gathered.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Oord-meaſure, or the table of boord-meaſure, is nothing els but that which ſheweth the length of a foote of boord or planke, at any breadth: though commonly we gather this meaſure, but for euery breadth from one inch to thirtie ſixe inches, and ſo ſet them downe in order, as in the table of boord-meaſure following, which is from one to thirtie. Now you may finde the length of a foote at any breadth thus. Diuide one hundred forty ſoure (which is the number of inches in a foote of boord) by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breadth that giuen, and the quotient will ſhew you how many inches makes a foote in length at that breadth. As for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Diuide one hundrech fortie foure by the breadth foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téene, and the quotient will be <hi>10 4/14</hi> or <hi>2/7,</hi> that is, the length of a foote at <hi>14</hi> inches broade, is <hi>10</hi> inches and two ſeauen parts of an inch. So diuide <hi>144</hi> by the breadth <hi>4,</hi> and the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2036:21"/>quotient will giue you <hi>36</hi> inches for the length of a foote at that breadth of <hi>4</hi> inches. This <hi>36</hi> diuided by <hi>12,</hi> will giue you in the quotient the number of féete therein, which is iuſt thrée.</p>
               <p>But if you will gather your table of boord-meaſure, for boordes that haue odde quarters of an inch in their breadth: then diuide <hi>576</hi> (which is the number of quarters in a foote of boord) by the number of quarters of inches in the breadth, and the quotient will giue you in inches, the length of a foote. As for example, let the breadth be <hi>7</hi> inches and a halfe: This is in all <hi>30</hi> quarters of an inch. By this <hi>30</hi> I diuide <hi>576,</hi> and the quotient is <hi>19 6/30</hi> or <hi>⅕,</hi> that is, the length of a foote is <hi>19</hi> inches and a fift part of an inch.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 12. How that meaſure which is called Timber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſure is gathered.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Imber-meaſure, or the Table of Timber-meaſure, is that which giueth the length of a foote of Timber at any ſquare. But our ordinarie Timber-meaſure is gathered, onely from the ſquare of one inch to the ſquare of <hi>36</hi> inches. It is thus gathered. Multiply the number of inches in euery ſquare, by it ſelfe: then by the ofcome or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, diuide <hi>1728</hi> (which is the number of inches contayned in a foote of Timber) and the quotient will giue you in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, the length of a foote of Timber at that ſquare. As for example: let the ſquare be <hi>18.</hi> This <hi>18</hi> multiplyed in it ſelfe, makes <hi>324:</hi> by which, diuide <hi>1728,</hi> and the quotient will be <hi>5 108/324</hi> or <hi>⅓,</hi> that is, the length of a foote, is <hi>5</hi> inches and one third part of an inch.</p>
               <p>But if you will gather your table of Timber-meaſure, for ſquares that haue odde halfes or quarters of an inch; then multiply the number of quarters of inches in the ſquare, by it ſelfe; and by the product or ofcome thereof, deuide
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2036:22"/>
                  <hi>27648</hi> (which is one fourth part of the quarters of inches contayned in a foote) and the quotient will giue you the length of a foote in inches: which you may reduce into féete, by diuiding them by <hi>12.</hi> As for example: let the ſquare be <hi>16</hi> and <hi>¾.</hi> Firſt I bring them into quarters, which is <hi>67.</hi> This <hi>67</hi> I multiply in it ſelfe, and it makes <hi>4489.</hi> By this <hi>4489</hi> I doe diuide <hi>27648,</hi> and the quotient will be <hi>6 714/4489</hi> which is <hi>6</hi> inches, and ſome what more then a ſixt part of an inch.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Table of Boord-meaſure.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough Maſter <hi>Digges</hi> in his ſaid Tectonicon, hath ſet downe two Tables, the one for boord-meaſure, and the other for Timber-meaſure: yet becauſe thoſe that here follow, doe differ, both in matter and fourme; I haue therefore ſet them downe, with this explication of them inſuing.</p>
               <p>But firſt note; that whereas Maſter <hi>Digges</hi> in both Tables, hath procéeded from one inch to <hi>36</hi> inches: I haue gon no farther then to <hi>30</hi> inches: and indéede it were no great matter, if they went but to <hi>24</hi> inches. For when the breadth of boord, or the ſquare of Timber, doe excéede <hi>24</hi> inches, but eſpecially <hi>30</hi> inches; then they giue ſo little for the length of a foote, as that the oft drawing of that length vpon the boord or Timber, cannot but bréede apparant error, except great héede be taken. Therefore for your boord, if it excéede <hi>30</hi> inches in breadth, you may meaſure it as if it were halfe ſo broade, and count euery foote for two foote. And as for your Timber, if the ſquare thereof excéede <hi>30</hi> inches, or rather <hi>24</hi> inches; then meaſure it as if it were halfe that ſquare (as for example, if the ſquare be <hi>32</hi> inches, then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coumpt it as <hi>16</hi> inches) and then accoumpt euery foote for foure foote.</p>
               <p>Note alſo that I haue left out of this Table of boord-mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure (of that which Maſter <hi>Digges</hi> hath ſet downe in his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2036:22"/>Table) what maketh a foote at any number of inches and an od quarter or three quarters of an inch, both becauſe they are not, neither can conueniently be ſet on the Rule, as alſo for that no loſſe of any moment comes by geſſing at them. And therefore I haue contented my ſelfe to ſet downe onely inches and halfe inches. But if any man like to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue iuſtly what maketh a foote of boord at any number of inches, and a quarter of an inch or thrée quarters of an inch, then either he may repaire to Maſter <hi>Digges</hi> his Table, or elſe let him finde it out by the way taught in the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth chapter of this ſecond part. But to returne to the meaning of this Table of boord-meaſure.</p>
               <p>In the row <hi>AB,</hi> is ſet downe one vnder another, the breadth of boords from one inch to <hi>30</hi> inches, as you may plainly perceiue by looking on it. Euery one of theſe numbers from one to <hi>30,</hi> I will call a <hi>Breadth.</hi> In the colum vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the letter <hi>C,</hi> is ſet downe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt euery breadth, the number of féete, inches, and parts of an inch, that make a foote in length at that breadth. (The féete in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the colums, ſtand in the narrow row, at the left ſide, and the inches and parts of an inch in
<table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">A</cell>
                        <cell role="label" cols="2">C</cell>
                        <cell role="label" cols="2">D</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>½</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>9 ⅗</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>5 1/7</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>4 ⅘</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>2 2/11</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>10 : 1/7</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>8 4/7</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>7 ⅕</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>4 16/17</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>3 3/19</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>2 ⅖</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>2 ¾</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>1 1/11</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>: ½</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>11 : ½</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>11 1/13</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>10 ⅔</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>10 2/7</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>9 : ⅞</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>9 ⅗</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>9 : 2/7</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>8 : ¾</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>8 ½</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>8 : ⅕</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>7 : ⅘</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>7 : 4/7</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>7 : ⅓</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>7 ⅕</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>7 1/41</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>6 6/7</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>6 : 5/7</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>6 : ½</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>6 : ⅜</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>6 : ¼</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>6 : ⅛</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>5 : ⅞</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>5 : ¾</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>5 11/17</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>5 : ½</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>5 : 3/7</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>5 ⅓</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>5 : 2/9</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>5 : 1/7</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>5 1/10</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>4 ⅞</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>4 ⅘</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>4 : 5/7</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:2036:23"/>the broder row at the right ſide thereof. Note alſo, that where as you ſée in the fractions, ſometimes one pricke, ſometimes two prickes, that when one pricke ſtands before the fractions it ſignifies a littelleſſe; and two prickes a little more.)</p>
               <p>Now if that the breadth of the boord be a certaine number of inches and one halfe inch, then is the length of a foote ouer againſt thoſe number of inches, in the colum vnder <hi>D.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But becauſe an example will giue more light then many words otherwiſe: Therefore ſuppoſe the boord to be <hi>11</hi> inches broade: then finde <hi>11</hi> in the row <hi>AB,</hi> and ouer againſt it in the colum <hi>C</hi> you ſhall ſée <hi>1.1</hi> and <hi>1/11,</hi> which is one foote, one inch, and one eleuenth part of an inch.</p>
               <p>But if the boord were <hi>11</hi> inches and <hi>½</hi> broad: then ſéeke the length of a foote ouer againſt that <hi>11,</hi> in the colum <hi>D,</hi> and it is <hi>12</hi> inches and <hi>½.</hi> So if the breadth of the boord were <hi>25</hi> inches and <hi>½:</hi> looke for <hi>25</hi> in the row <hi>AB,</hi> and ouer againſt it in the colum <hi>D,</hi> you ſhall ſée fiue inches and fiue ſeauenth parts of an inch. And let this ſuffice for the Table of boord-meaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Table of Timber-meaſure.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the row <hi>AB</hi> is ſet downe the ſquares of Timber from one inch to <hi>30</hi> inches. Ouer againſt euery one of theſe, in the colum vnder <hi>C,</hi> is ſet downe the length of a foote, in féete and inches, and parts of an inch. The féete are ſet downe in the row at the left hand of this columas farre as the ſquares doe yeld a foote, and the inches and parts of an inch are ſet downe in the row towards the left hand of the ſame colum.</p>
               <p>But if the ſquares of the péece of timber be any number of inches betwéene <hi>1</hi> and <hi>10,</hi> and an od halfe inch more: then ouer againſt thoſe number of inches in the colum vnder <hi>D,</hi> you ſhall finde the length of a foote, in féete, inches and parts of an inch: the féete ſtanding (as in the other colum) in the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2036:23"/>row at the left ſide there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and the inches &amp; parts of an inch, in the row at the right ſide. The reaſon why I added thoſe halfe inches from <hi>1</hi> to <hi>10,</hi> is, becauſe in meaſuring of Timber by deducting the loſt ſquare, as is ſet down in the fourth chapter of this ſecond part of this booke, you ſhal haue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion oft times to ſéeke out the length of a foote for a ſquare of one inch and a halfe, two inches and <hi>½,</hi> thrée inches and <hi>½,</hi> and ſo forth to ten inches.</p>
               <p>Here farther it is to be noted, that whereas you ſhall finde for the moſt part before the numera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for of the fractions, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times one pricke, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times two prickes: that one pricke doth ſignifie ſomewhat leſſe, and two prickes doth ſignifie ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more. This I haue noted, as Maſter <hi>Digges</hi> hath alſo don, though it matters not whether ſuch <hi>more</hi> or <hi>leſſe,</hi> were obſerued or not, ſéeing no ſenſible error comes by omitting them.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">A</cell>
                        <cell role="label" cols="2">C</cell>
                        <cell role="label" cols="2">D</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>½</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>144</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>64</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>½</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>9 1/16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>1 ⅓</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>9 3/25</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>9 : ⅛</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>4 : 8/9</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>11 : 2/7</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>4 : ¾</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>11 : 12/13</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>9 ⅓</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>7 1/7</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>5 : 2/7</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>2 : 2/7</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>10 : ⅕</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>8 : 13/16</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>7 : ⅔</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>6 ¾</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>5 ⅓</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>4 : 25/32</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>4 : 5/16</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>3 : 11/12</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>3 : 4/7</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>3 : ¼</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>2 : ¾</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>2 : 9/16</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>2 : ⅜</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>2 : ⅕</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>2 : 1/16</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>1 : 11/12</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:2036:24"/>
               <p>An example or two in this caſe ſhall not be vnneceſſarie. If the ſquare of the péece giuen be fiue inches, finde fiue in the row <hi>AB,</hi> and ouer againſt it in the colum of <hi>C,</hi> you ſhall finde fiue foote nine inches and thrée twentie fiue parts of an inch. If the ſquare giuen be thirtéene, then ouer againſt thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téene you ſhall finde on the right ſide of the colum <hi>C, 10⅕:</hi> which is <hi>10</hi> inches and ſomewhat more then one fift part of an inch, if the ſquare giuen be ſixe inches and a halfe: then ouer againſt ſixe, you ſhall finde the colum <hi>D</hi> for the length of a foote, thrée foote foure inches and ſomewhat leſſe then eight ninth parts of an inch: more exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples néedes not. Enough hath béen ſaid to any that is but of meane capacitie and deſirous to learne.</p>
               <trailer>The end of the ſecond part.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:2036:24"/>
            <head>THE THIRD PART OF THE CARPENTERS RVLE, Containing ſundrie true waies to meaſure <hi>ſuperficies and ſollids, or (as wee call them) Boords and Timber, of extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie formes.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER. 1. The meaning of certaine tearmes of Geometrie generally vſed in this third part.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I had written the former part of this booke concerning meaſuring of ordinarie Timber and Boord, and did conſider, that beſides the pleaſure, there would come ſome good to Carpenters, if they could alſo meaſure extraordinarie fourmes: I haue therefore thought good to adde this part vnto the other two. True it is, that Maſter <hi>Digs</hi> in his Tectonicon hath not béen ſilent of the moſt of theſe things. But becauſe he applies them to meaſuring of land, few or none doe thinke that they belong alſo to meaſuring of Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: and therefore my labour I hope is not vnneceſſarie, though I ſhould but haue repeated the ſame thing and apply them to our vſe, without adding any other thing.</p>
               <p>I haue knowne ſome that would buy whole frames rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die wrought by meaſure: but ſure I am that no Carpenter could haue meaſured it for them, without the knowledge of that which is written hereafter.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:2036:25"/>
               <p>And becauſe I ſhall haue occaſion to vſe many tearmes of Geometrie, by which I may with more eaſe deliuer, and you with more plainnes perceiue my minde in theſe things: I haue therefore ſet downe the meaning, as plainly as I can, of ſome Geometricall tearmes, which moſt ſerue for our preſent purpoſe. And in this Chapter I explaine onely thoſe tearmes that generally I vſe throughout this whole part, and which doe not properly belong to any one chapter. The reſt I will declare in the beginning of euery chapter, as the matter thereof giues occaſion. But to the matter.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> An Angle is nothing els but a corner, made by the mée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of two lines (for I ſpeake not of ſollid Angles).</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> A right Angle (which wee call a ſquire or a ſquare Angle) is that whoſe two lines comprehending or making the Angle, ſtand perpendicular or plumbe the one to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> An oblique Angle (which we call beuell or ſkew) is euery angle not being a right angle, whether it be greater or leſſe, or (as we ſay) whether it ſpread or clitch.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4.</hi> A Superficies, is that which hath onely length and breadth, and no thicknes at all. Here note, that whereas we call boords, ſuperficies, and Timber ſollids, it is not becauſe a boord is not a ſollid (for it hath length, breadth and thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) but becauſe we reſpect not (in meaſuring of them) but only their length and breadth.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5.</hi> A Sollid (or a bodie) is that which hath length, breadth, and thicknes.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6.</hi> Parallels are thoſe lines, ſuperficies, or ſollids, that differ euery where alike, or are not néerer together in one place then in another.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7.</hi> A Figure, is any kinde of ſuperficies or ſollid that is bounded about, as Triangles, Squares, Circles, Globes, Cones, Priſmes, and the reſt.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>8.</hi> The Baſe of a Figure, is any ſide (as wee may ſay) thereof, vpon which it may be ſuppoſed to ſtand. Or if you take any ſide of a figure for the ground or bottome or lower part thereof, that ſame is the Baſe.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:2036:25"/>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>9.</hi> The height of a figure, is the length of a Perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar or plumme line falling from the top thereof, to the baſe, ground, or bottome thereof. And whether this Perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar or plum line fall within or without the figure, it makes no matter, ſo as it be neither higher nor lower then the baſe or bottome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 2. How to raiſe and let fall a Perpendicular.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Perpendicular line is that which ſtands plumme vpright vpon another, leaning neither the one way nor the other. A Perpendicular is ſaid to be raiſed, when a point is giuen in a line, from which it muſt riſe. It is ſaid to bée let fall, when a point is giuen aboue the line, from which it muſt fall.</p>
               <p>Now beſides that you may both raiſe and let fall a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicular by a ſquire or ſquare: there are many waies Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrically to doe both the one and the other. And becauſe there is eſpeciall vſe in this third part, of letting fall a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicular or plumme line from a point giuen, as alſo from an angle in a figure to the baſe: I would not haue men ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant how to doe the ſame without a ſquire, which is not alwaies at hand, when a rule &amp; paire of compaſſes are. And yet I will ſet downe onely one way of many, to auoide te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſnes, which is thus.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Let the point giuen be <hi>A,</hi> the line giuen <hi>BC.</hi> Open the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes to any diſtance conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, and ſetting one foote in the point <hi>A,</hi> make an arke or péece of a Circle with the other foote, till it cut the line <hi>BC</hi> twice. Thoſe two places of cutting we call Interſections,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2036:26"/>and are here in this example at <hi>B</hi> and <hi>C.</hi> Then finde the middle betwéene thoſe two Interſections, and from that middle draw a line to the point <hi>A</hi> (which is the point giuen) and that line ſhal be perpendicular or plumbe from the point <hi>A</hi> to the line <hi>B C,</hi> as was required.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 3. Of a Triangle and a Priſme, what they are, and how they be meaſured.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Triangles are diuers, both in reſpect of their ſides and angles, and may bee meaſured diuers waies: But let this one way ſerue for all. Multiplie halfe of the baſe by all the height or perpendicular: Or (which is all one) multiplie all the baſe by halfe the height or perpendicular; and either of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts giues the content of the Triangle.</p>
               <p>Here I pray you remember what I meane by the baſe and height or altitude, according as was ſhe wed in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Chapter. In this figure you may ſuppoſe the longeſt line to be the baſe, and then the prickt line is the height or perpendicular.</p>
               <p>Now note, that a Priſme is that whoſe two oppoſite plaines or ends be equall, like, and parallell, the other ſides being parallelograms, that is, figures whoſe oppoſite ſides are equall, and whoſe angles be all right angles. So that euery péece of timber may be called a Priſme, not being bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at one end then at another, of what faſhion ſoeuer it be,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2036:26"/>whether the baſe or end thereof be of thrée ſides, as cants; or of foure, fiue, ſixe, or more ſides, as other timber; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſides be of equall length or of vnequall.</p>
               <p>How to meaſure any Priſme or péece of timber of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer fourme or faſhion the baſe or end thereof is; you néede but multiplie the content of the baſe or end by the altitude or height, or (as wee call it) the length of the péece, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct giues the content thereof.</p>
               <p>This might ſerue once for all, as ſufficient to meaſure ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lids or timber, whoſe baſes or ends are like and equall: ſo that it néeded not but to teach how to meaſure euery kinde of baſe, as Triangles, Quadrangles, &amp;c. But yet for plainnes ſake, I will giue examples of euery forme, with ſome varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of meaſuring them, when I ſpeake of meaſuring plaine fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures as being their baſes.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Therefore if the baſe of your Priſme or péece of tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber were the ſaid figure <hi>A,</hi> multiplte the content of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle <hi>A</hi> by the length of the péece, and the product giues the content thereof.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Or els you may meaſure that Priſme or péece of tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thus: Take the whole perpendicular, and ſuppoſe it to be one ſide of a ſquared péece of timber (as we call it) and take halfe the baſe for the other ſide: and ſo meaſure it by any of the waies taught in the ſecond part of this booke.</p>
               <p>This being vnderſtood which is here written, the vſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is very generall. For beſides that the Carpenter may meaſure hereby any canted péece of timber, as ſteps for ſtaires, and canted railes, and ſuch like: the plaiſterer alſo, who often worketh by the yard, may hereby meaſure gable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ends, and ſuch like fourmes. The Glaſier hath likewiſe vſe hereof: and alſo it may ſtand the Maſon oft in ſtead.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:2036:27"/>
               <head>CHAP. 4. What a Parallelogram is, and how it is meaſured.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Parallelogram is a figure whoſe oppoſit ſides are equall,
<note place="margin">Note that whereas I ſay all right angles, it is but to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh betwixt this figure, and the two next follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing, for they are Parallelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grams alſo.</note> and whoſe angles or corners are all right or ſquare angles: ſuch as is the figure <hi>B.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>It is meaſured thus: Multiplie the length by the breadth, and the product or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come giues the content.</p>
               <p>The priſme or péece of tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber whoſe baſes or ends are pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallelograms, as is the ſaid fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure <hi>B,</hi> you may meaſure thus: Multiplie the content of the baſe by the length, and the product yéelds the ſollid content, as is taught in the ſeuenth Chapter of the ſecond part of this booke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 5. What a Rombus is, and how it is meaſured.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Rombus, other wiſe called a Diamond forme, is a figure of foure equall ſides &amp; oblique angles: Or, the ſides are all of one length, and none of the angles are ſquare, ſuch as is the figure <hi>B.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The meaſure of a Rombus is thus. Multiplie the length of one of the ſides, by the perpendicular plumme line, drawne from that ſide to the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite ſide, which in this figure is the prickt line, and the product yéelds the content.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:2036:27"/>
               <p n="1">1. The priſme or péece of timber whoſe baſes are a Rom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, is meaſured thus. Multiplie the content of the baſe or end by the length, and the product giues your deſire.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Or els (as in the third Chapter of this part) take all the perpendicular for one ſide of a ſquared péece, and one ſide of the figure <hi>B</hi> for the other ſide of the ſquared péece, and ſo meaſure it by any of the waies taught in the ſecond part of this booke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 6. What a Romboides is, and how it is meaſured.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Romboides (called a Diamond-like figure) is that whoſe oppoſite ſides and oppoſite angles are equall. But all the ſides are not equall, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is any of the angles right: ſuch is this fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure <hi>C.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The meaſure dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth nothing from the meaſuring of a Rombus in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Chapter, and might well haue bin ſoyned together: ſo that he that can mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure one can meaſure both. But to the former waies you may adde this, if you pleaſe. Firſt diuide it into two Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angles, as here this figure is by the prickt line. Then mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure one of thoſe Triangles by the way ſet downe in the third Chapter of this part: the double whereof is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of this figure. The like is alſo to be done with a Rom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus or a Parallelogram.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>The Priſme or péece of timber whoſe baſes are a Rom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boides, is meaſured as a péece whoſe baſe is a Rombus, as in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2036:28"/>the former Chapter. But if you meaſure the baſe or end by two Triangles, as in this Chapter, then take as for the ſides of a ſquared péece of timber, all the perpendicular of one of the Triangles, and all the baſe of the ſame Triangle, and ſo meaſure it by any of the waies taught in the ſecond part.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 7. What a Trapezium is, and how it is meaſured.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Trapezium is a figure of foure ſides, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing all the ſides and angles equall, as is the figure <hi>D.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is meaſured thus. Firſt diuide it into two Triangles, by drawing a line from one angle to the oppoſite angle; as here the figure <hi>D</hi> is diuided by the prickt line. Then meaſure by the way taught in the third Chap. of this 3. part, both thoſe triangles, ſeuerally: and adde both their contents for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the whole Trapezium.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p n="1">1. The priſme or péece of timber, whoſe end or baſe is a trapezium, as the trapezium <hi>D,</hi> may be thus meaſured. Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplie the content of the baſe or end, by the length of the péece, and the product giues the content thereof.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Or els, take the ſquare roote of the content of the haſe or end <hi>D;</hi> and ſo meaſure it by any of the waſes taught in the ſecond part.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Orels, ſuppoſe the péece to be cut into two Cants, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the baſe or end thereof <hi>D</hi> is diuided. Then mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure both thoſe Cants, by the way taught in the third chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this part, and take the ſumme of thoſe two Cants for the content of the whole péece.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:2036:28"/>
               <head>CHAP. 8. What a regular mani-ſided figure is, and how it is meaſured.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Mani-ſided figure, is that which hath more ſides then foure. They are either regular or irregular. A regular mani-ſided figure is that whoſe ſides and angles are al equal, as is this figure marked with <hi>A.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>An irregular, is that whoſe ſides or angles are vnequall.</p>
               <p>A regular mani-ſided figure is thus meaſured. Firſt draw a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicular from the center of the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure to the middle of one of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſides, as is the ſhort prickt line in the ſaid figure <hi>A.</hi> Then ſeeke the length or compaſſe about of all the ſides: the halfe whereof you muſt multiplie by the length of the ſaid perpendicular, and the product giues the content of the figure.</p>
               <p>Now the center of a regular mani-ſided figure is thus found: Raiſe a perpendicular vpon the middle of any two of the ſides not being directly oppoſite, and where they inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſect or cut one another, there is the center of the figure.</p>
               <p>By this may you finde the center of a Circle, or of any péece of a circle, namely, if you draw any two right lines, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther equall or vnequall, in the circle or péece of the circle, and from their middles doe raiſe perpendiculars: I ſay, the méeting of thoſe perpendiculars, is the center of the circle or péece of a circle.</p>
               <p>But if the figure haue an euen number of ſides, as 6, 8, 10, and ſo foorth; then you néede but draw a line from any two oppoſite angles, and another line from any two other oppoſite angles: and where thoſe two lines doe cut, there
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2036:29"/>is the center of the figure. Thus haue I drawne the two long prickt lines to finde the center of this figure <hi>A.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> The priſme or péece of timber whereof the figure <hi>A,</hi> or any other regular mani-ſided figure is the baſe or end, is meaſured by multiplying the content of the baſe by the length of the péece, and the product giues the ſollid content.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Or els, take the halfe of all the ſides or compaſſe about as for one ſide of a ſquared péece of timber, and the ſaid per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicular for the other ſide, and ſo meaſure it by any of the waies taught in the ſecond part.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 9. How irregular mani-ſided figures are meaſured.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Rregular mani-ſided figures, as alſo regular mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſided figures, may be thus meaſured. Diuide the figure into triangles, as here I haue diuided the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure <hi>B</hi> by certen prickt lines. Then meaſure each triangle by it ſelfe, as is taught in the third Chapter of this part, and adde the contents of all the Triangles together; and their ſumme or totall is the content of the figure.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> The priſme or péece of timber, whoſe baſe or end is the figure <hi>B,</hi> or any other vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equall mani-ſided figure, is meaſured by multiplying the content of the baſe or end in the length of the péece, and the product giues the ſollid content.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Or els, take the ſquare roote of the number of inches in the content of the baſe, and ſo meaſure it by any of the waies taught in the ſecond part of this booke.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> And becauſe for the meaſuring of enery ſort of timber
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2036:29"/>I haue vſed to ſet downe ſome way by which it may be done without Arithmeticke: Therefore for a third way; as euery triangle in the figure <hi>B</hi> is meaſured, ſo meaſure ſo many ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lids whereof the triangles be the baſes, and whoſe lengths are y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> length of the irregular péece of timber, as is taught in the third Chapter of this third part; and then adde all their contents for the content of the whole péece.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 10. What a Circle, a Semicircle, and a Sector are, and how they be meaſured.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Circle is a figure, plaine and round.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> The round line y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> makes the Circle is called the Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> The point in the middle of the circle is called y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Center.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4.</hi> The line (and indéed eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie line) paſſing by the Center to both ſides of the Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, is called the Diameter, as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> black line in this circle <hi>C.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5.</hi> Halfe the Diameter, and indeede euery line paſſing from the Center to the Circumference, is called the Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diameter.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6.</hi> Al lines in the Circle (except the Diameter) which are drawne from ſide to ſide, are called Cords. Such is the prickt line in the circle <hi>C.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7.</hi> The Diameter cuts the circle into two equall parts; each of which parts is called a Semicircle.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>8.</hi> A cord cuts the circle into two vnequall parts; each of which parts is called a Section of a Circle. The one is called the greater ſection, becauſe it is greater then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Semicircle.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2036:30"/>The other is called the leſſer ſection, becauſe it is leſſe then the ſemicircle.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>9</hi> A Sector is any part of a circle, either greater or leſſer then a ſemicircle, contained vnder two ſemidiameters mée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the center, and a péece of the circumference.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>10</hi> Note that the circumference of a circle is triple the diameter, and almoſt one ſeauenth part more. But we count it as iuſt triple and one ſeauenth part, or as 22 is to 7. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to finde the circumference, the diameter being knowne; multiply your diameter by <hi>22.</hi> and diuide the product by <hi>7,</hi> and the quotient ſhe wes you the circumference.</p>
               <p>Now to meaſure a circle doe thus.
<note place="margin">To meaſure a Circle.</note> Multiplie halfe the diameter by halfe the circumference; or all the diameter by a quarter of the circumference; or all the circumference by a quarter of the diameter; and any of the products giues the content of the circle.</p>
               <p>The Semicircle is thus meaſured.
<note place="margin">To mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micircle.</note> Multiply halfe the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ameter in halfe the arke or arch thereof; or all the diameter in a quarter of the arke thereof, &amp;c. And either of the products giues the content of the ſemicircle.</p>
               <p>A Sector is meaſured as a ſemicircle,
<note place="margin">To mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure a Sec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</note> namely by Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying halfe the ſemidiameter in halfe the arke or arch there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, &amp;c. the product whereof is the content of the ſector.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The ſollid or péece of Timber whoſe end or baſe is a circle, a ſemicircle, or a ſector, may be thus meaſured. Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the content of the baſe or end in the length of the peece, and the product giues the ſollid content.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2</hi> Or, take the ſemidiameter for one ſide of a ſquared péece of Timber, and halfe the arke (be it of a circle, ſemicircle or ſector) for the other ſide, and ſo meaſure it by any of the wayes taught in the ſecond part.</p>
               <p>Here it were not vnneceſſarie to ſhew how to finde the quantitie of an arke or péece of a circle. But of the diuers wayes that are found, you may vſe this. Firſt hauing taken the length of your ſemidiameter in any meaſure, which let be for more conueniencie in
<note n="*" place="margin">For the greater meaſure the greater error in this kinde of worke.</note> inches, then open your compaſſes
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2036:30"/>to an inch, and ſée how many of them is contained in your arke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 11. How to meaſure Sections of a Circle.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Told you in the laſt chapter that there be two ſorts of ſections, a greater which is more then a ſemicir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle; and a leſſer, which is not ſo much as a ſemicir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. They are meaſured diuerſely.</p>
               <p>A greater ſection is thus meaſured,
<note place="margin">To mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Section.</note> draw two ſemidiame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from either end of the arke to the center, as the two prickt lines in the figure <hi>A.</hi> Then Multiply halfe the arke in the ſemidiameter, and to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct thereof adde the content of the ſaid triangle, made of the cord and the two ſemidiame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and the totall will be the content of the whole ſection.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>The ſollid or péece of Timber, whoſe baſe is the figure <hi>A</hi> or any greater ſection of a circle, is found as before is oft ſaid, by multiplying the content of the baſe in the length of the péece.</p>
               <p>Or take halfe the arke as one ſide of a ſquared péece of Timber, and the ſemidiameter as the other ſide, and ſo mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure it by any of the wayes in the ſecond part: then adde thereunto the content of the ſollid, whereof the triangle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore named is the baſe, and the totall will be the content of the ſollid, whoſe end is the ſaid ſection.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:2036:31"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>The ſollid or péece of timber, whoſe baſe or end is the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure <hi>B,</hi> or any leſſer ſection of a circle, may be meaſured as before is taught, by multiplying the content of the figure in the length of the ſollid.</p>
               <p>Or els, take halfe the arke as one ſide of a ſquared péece of timber, and the ſemidiameter for the other ſide, and ſo meaſure it by the waies in the ſecond part of this book. Then deduct out of the content thereof, the content of the ſollid or péece of timber, whereof the triangle made of the corde and the two ſemidiameters, is the baſe or end: and the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is the content of the ſollid, made vpon the ſaid leſſer ſec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>B.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the <hi>6.</hi> chapter of the ſecond part of this book,
<note place="margin">To mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall.</note> I told you that I would ſhew you in the end of this Chapter, how to meaſure an Ouall: which in a word is thus. Firſt finde (by that which is taught in the <hi>8.</hi> Chapter of this part) the foure centers of the foure arkes or péeces of circles, whereof the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall is made (for euery Ouall is made, by ioyning together foure ſeuerall arkes or péeces of circles, whereof thoſe at the two ends are equall, and thoſe at the two ſides are alſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall). Then hauing found thoſe arkes, draw their corde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them: ſo ſhall you ſee the whole Ouall to be diuided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to foure leſſer ſections of a circle and a parallelogram. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore meaſure all thoſe foure ſections, as afore is taught in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2036:31"/>this Chapter; and meaſure alſo the parallelogram, by the way taught in the third Chapter of this third part: and the content of them all (that is, of thoſe foure ſections and the parailelogram) is the content of the Ouall.</p>
               <p>Nete, that when you haue meaſured one ſection at the end of the Ouall, you haue alſo the content of the other ſec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at the other end (becauſe they are equall): Therefore you néede but to double the one, and ſo you haue the content of them both. In like ſort may you doe with the ſections at the ſides, that is; hauing meaſured the one, doe but double it for the content of them both.</p>
               <p>If a péece of timber were Ouall faſhion, that is, had his baſe or end like an Ouall: then it may be meaſured by mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying the content of the baſe by the altitude or length of the péece, as hath béen often mentioned.</p>
               <p>Note further, that by this which is here taught, and by that which is afore written of triangles and mani-ſided fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, you may meaſure any kinde of figure, either plaine or ſollid, that is made of ſtraight lines and circular lines toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if you doe but vſe diligence, and diuide or imagine a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion of the whole figure into his proper ſections and other figures as becommeth; and ſo meaſure thoſe ſections and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther figures ſeuerally, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adde their contents together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 12. What a Pyramis is, and how it is meaſured.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Pyramis is a ſollid figure, contained vnder many plaine ſuperficies ſet vpon one plaine ſuperficies, and gathered together into one point, as this py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramis <hi>A,</hi> Pyramids are diuers according as their baſes be diuers, as of <hi>3, 4, 5,</hi> or more ſides, as is at large ſhewed in the <hi>10.</hi> definition of the <hi>11.</hi> booke of <hi>Euclides</hi> Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Geometrie.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:2036:32"/>
               <p>But of what ſorts ſoeuer the pyramids be,
<note place="margin">To mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the ſollid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of a Pyramis.</note> they are mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by one rule, which is thus: Multiplie the altitude or height by the third part of the content of the baſe: or contrarily, multiplie the content of the baſe by the third part of the altitude or height, and either of the products is the content ſollid of the pyramis.</p>
               <p>Here note, that the altitude or height is not the length of the ſide of the pyramis, but (as I told you in the firſt chapter of this third part) it is the length of the perpendicular or plumme line, falling from the point or top thereof, to the baſe or bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>But if you would meaſure the ſuperficies or outſide of a pyramis:
<note place="margin">To mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficiall content of a Pyramis.</note> then (in ſo much as all the ſides are triangles) meaſure euery triangle by it ſelfe, and to all their contents adde the content of the baſe, and the totall or ſumme is the ſuperficiall content of the pyramis.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 13. How to meaſure parts of a pyramis, or timber that is taper growne.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F a part of a pyramis doe taper much, you may lay it on a paper by a ſcale, and make it out to a perfect pyramis. Hauing ſo done, meaſure the whole py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramis. Meaſure alſo that part thereof which was added; which ſubſtract or take from the content of the whole pyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis, and the remainder giues the content of the péece of a py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramis. This way is not conuenient in ordinarie tapered timber, and therefore take rather the way here following.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:2036:32"/>
               <p>You know that in the laſt chapter of the firſt part of this booke, I told you, that if a tapered péece were meaſured by the ſquare of the middle, there was loſt to the ſeller a péece of timber, whoſe length is the ſixt part of the length of the whole péece; and which hath for his breadth, halfe the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the breadth of both ends; and for his thicknes, halfe the difference of the thicknes of both ends. Therefore ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing meaſured the peece by the ſquare of the middle, deduct the ſaid loſt péece, and the remainder is the content of the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered péece. This loſt péece you may meaſure (and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct) thus. Take the halfe of the difference of the breadth of both ends of the tapered péece, for the breadth of your loſt péece; and halfe the difference of the thicknes of both ends, for the thicknes of the loſt péece: &amp; with that breadth and thicknes meaſure it according to the length; which (as I ſaid) is the ſixt part of the length of the whole péece. And note, that by the length, I meane not the ſide of the tapered péece, but the plumme or height thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 14. What a Cone is, and how it is meaſured.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Cone is a round pyramis (as it were) which hath for the baſe a Circle, as is this figure. It is largely deſcribed in the <hi>18.</hi> definition of the <hi>11.</hi> booke of <hi>Euclides</hi> Elements.
<note place="margin">To mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the ſollid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of a Cone.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The ſollid content of a Cone is thus meaſured: Multiplie the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the baſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> third part of the height, and the product is the ſollid content of the Cone.
<note place="margin">To mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficiall content of a Cone.</note>
               </p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Note here againe, that the ſide of the Cone is not the height, plumme or perpendicular line from the top to the baſe, but the length of the ridge or ſloping of the Cone.</p>
               <p>There are many other kinds of plaines and ſollids, but I may not ſtand to write of them. If any man, either for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or profit, ſhall deſire to know them, or their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, let him looke into <hi>Euclides</hi> Elements, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Digs</hi> his Pantametria, Maſter <hi>Lucars</hi> Solace, and other good books of Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrie, which are extant in Engliſh.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2036:33"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
